noticed that the milk had disappeared.
Chapter 3.
How they toiled and sweated to get the hay in.
But their efforts were rewarded, for the harvest was an even bigger success than they had hoped.
Sometimes the work was hard. The implements had been designed for human
beings and not for animals.
And it was a great drawback that no animal was able to use any tool that
involved standing on his hind legs.
But the pigs were so clever that they could think of a way round every difficulty.
As for the horses, they knew every inch of the field, and in fact, understood
the business of mowing and raking far better than Jones and his men had ever done.
The pigs did not actually work, but directed and supervised the others.
With their superior knowledge, it was natural that they should assume the leadership.
Boxer and Clover would harness themselves to the cutter or the horse
rake. No bits or reins were needed in these days, of course, and steadily round and round the
field with a pig walking behind and calling out, "Gee up, comrade."
or "Whoa back, comrade."
as the case might be.
And every animal, down to the humblest, worked at turning the hay and gathering it.
Even the ducks and hens toiled to and fro all day in the sun, carrying tiny
wisps of hay in their beaks.
In the end, they finished the harvest in two days less time than it had usually
taken Jones and his men.
Moreover, it was the the harvest that the farm had ever seen.
There was no wastage whatever.
The hens and ducks, with their sharp eyes, had gathered up the very last stalk.
And not an animal on the farm had stolen so much as a mouthful.
All through that summer, the work of the farm went like clockwork.
The animals were happy as they had never conceived it possible to be.
Every mouthful of food was an acute, positive pleasure now that it was truly
their own food, produced by themselves and for themselves, not doled out to them by a grudging
master.
With the worthless, parasitical human beings gone, there was more for everyone to eat.
There was more leisure, too.
Inexperienced though the animals were, they met with many difficulties. For
instance, later in the year, when they harvested the corn, they had to tread it
out in the ancient style and blow away the chaff with their breath, since the
farm possessed no threshing machine.
But the pigs, with their cleverness, and Boxer, with his tremendous muscles,
always pulled them through.
Boxer was the admiration of everybody.
He had been a hard worker even in Jones's time, but now he seemed more like three horses
than one.
There were days when the entire work of the farm seemed to rest upon his mighty shoulders.
From morning to night, he was pushing and pulling, always at the spot where
the work was hardest.
He had made an arrangement with one of the cockerels to call him in the
mornings half an hour earlier than anyone else, and would put in some
volunteer labor at whatever seemed to be most needed before the regular day's work began.
His answer to every problem, every setback was, >> I will work harder.
>> Which he had adopted as his personal motto.
But everyone worked according to his capacity.
The hens and ducks, for instance, saved five bushels of corn at the harvest by
gathering up the stray grains.
Nobody stole, nobody grumbled over his rations. The quarreling and biting and
jealousy, which had been normal features of life in the old days, had almost disappeared.
Nobody shirked, or almost nobody.
Mollie, it was true, was not good at getting up in the mornings and had a way
of leaving work early on the ground that there was a stone in her hoof.
And the behavior of the cat was somewhat peculiar.
It was soon noticed that when there was work to be done, the cat could never be found.
She would vanish for hours on end and then reappear at meal times or in the
evening after work was over as though nothing had happened.
But she always made such excellent excuses and purred so affectionately
that it was impossible not to believe in her good intentions.
Old Benjamin, the donkey, seemed quite unchanged since the rebellion.
He did his work in the same slow, obstinate way as he had done it in
Jones's time, never shirking and never volunteering for extra work, either.
About the rebellion and its results, he would express no opinion.
When asked whether he was not happier now that Jones was gone, he would say only,
>> Donkeys live a long time.
None of you has ever seen a dead donkey.
And the others had to be content with this cryptic answer.
On Sundays, there was no work. Breakfast was an hour later than usual, and after
breakfast, there was a ceremony, which was observed every week without fail.
First came the hoisting of the flag.
Snowball had found in the harness room an old green tablecloth of Mrs. Jones's
and had painted on it a hoof and a horn in white.
This was run up the flagstaff in the farmhouse garden every Sunday morning.
The flag was green, Snowball explained, to represent the green fields of
England, while the hoof and horn signified the future Republic of the
animals, which would arise when the human race had been finally overthrown.
After the hoisting of the flag, all the animals trooped into the big barn for a
general assembly, which was known as the meeting.
Here, the work of the coming week was planned out, and resolutions were put forward and debated.
It was always the pigs who put forward the resolutions.
The other animals understood how to vote, but could never think of any resolutions of their own.
Snowball and Napoleon were by far the most active in the debates.
But it was noticed that these two were never in agreement. Whatever suggestion
either of them made, the other could be counted on to oppose it.
Even when it was resolved, a thing no one could object to in itself, to set
aside the small paddock behind the orchard as a home of rest for animals
who were past work, there was a stormy debate over the correct retiring age for
each class of animal.
The meeting always ended with the singing of Beasts of England, and the
afternoon was given up to recreation.
The pigs had set aside the harness room as a headquarters for themselves. Here,
in the evenings, they studied blacksmithing, carpentering, and other
necessary arts from books which they had brought out of the farmhouse.
Snowball also busied himself with organizing the other animals into what
he called animal committees.
He was indefatigable at this.
He formed the egg production committee for the hens, the Clean Tails League for
the cows, the Wild Comrades Re-education Committee.
The object of this was to tame the rats and rabbits, the Whiter Wool Movement for the sheep,
and various others.
Besides instituting classes in reading and writing, on the whole, these projects were a failure.
The attempt to tame the wild creatures, for instance, broke down almost immediately.
They continued to behave very much as before, and when treated with
generosity, simply took advantage of it.
The cat joined the Re-education Committee and was very active in it for some days.
She was seen one day sitting on a roof and talking to some sparrows who were
just out of her reach.
She was telling them that all animals were now comrades and that any sparrow
who chose could come and perch on her paw.
But the sparrows kept their distance.
The reading and writing classes, however, were a great success.
By the autumn, almost every animal on the farm was literate in some degree.
As for the pigs, they could already read and write perfectly.
The dogs learned to read fairly well, but were not interested in reading
anything except the Seven Commandments.
Muriel, the goat, could read somewhat better than the dogs, and sometimes used
to read to the others in the evenings from scraps of newspaper which she found
on the rubbish heap.
Benjamin could read as well as any pig, but never exercised his faculty.
So far as he knew, he said, there was nothing worth reading.
Clover learned the whole alphabet but could not put words together.
Boxer could not get beyond the letter D.
He would trace out A, B, C, D in the dust with his great hoof, and then would
stand staring at the letters with his ears back, sometimes shaking his forelock, trying
with all his might to remember what came next and never succeeding.
On several occasions indeed, he did learn E, F, G, H,
but by the time he knew them, it was always discovered that he had forgotten
A, B, C, and D.
Finally, he decided to be content with the first four letters and used to write
them out once or twice every day to refresh his memory.
Mollie refused to learn any but the six letters which spelt her own name.
She would form these very neatly out of pieces of twig and would then decorate
them with a flower or two and walk round them admiring them.
None of the other animals on the farm could get further than the letter A.
It was also found that the stupider animals, such as the sheep, hens, and
ducks, were unable to learn the seven commandments by heart.
After much thought, Snowball declared that the seven commandments could, in
effect, be reduced to a single maxim, namely four legs good, two legs bad.